<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Fey of Ravnica]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Fey of Ravnica</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:44:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:44:25 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Justice]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Vedalken who serves as the official envoy of the Azorius to the Expedition Corps. Was previously an enforcer, was promoted to judge the day before the invasion. Interested in the laws, customs, and history of other worlds.]]></description><link>npcs/justice.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Justice.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:08:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Twinless]]></title><description><![CDATA[A lazotep covered Jackal zombie. Part of Nicol Bolas’ invasion force died in the invasion. Was brought back by Lillianna more times than any other. Revived by the Golgari for them to study the necromancy of other worlds. Official envoy of the Golgari to the Expedition Corps.]]></description><link>npcs/twinless.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Twinless.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:06:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rank and File]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Loxodon and Rhino-guy who act as the official envoys of the Boros legion to the Expedition Corps. Offer training and additional manpower for expeditions as well as interested in any fresh recruits that can be brought back from a mission.]]></description><link>npcs/rank-and-file.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Rank and File.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:05:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Casper]]></title><description><![CDATA[A ghost who acts as the official envoy of the Orzhov guild to the REC. Is in charge of payroll for the Corp and is willing to offer loans to characters.]]></description><link>npcs/casper.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Casper.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:58:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Grug]]></title><description><![CDATA[An orc who wears nothing but a loincloth. A Gruul beast master for the Expedition Corps. Helps tame rampaging monsters brought through the planar portal. Keeps a menagerie of fierce beasts to train Corps members against to help prepare them for the rigors of planar travel.]]></description><link>npcs/grug.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Grug.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:56:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Straken aka Doctopus]]></title><description><![CDATA[A humanoid with feathers and scales. A Simic researcher working with the Expedition Corps to study xenobiology. Also under direct orders from Niv-Mizzet to study Doctor Magnificent and the effects the Firemind exposure had on him. Doctor Magnificent is the one who gave her the unfortunate moniker of Doctopus.]]></description><link>npcs/straken-aka-doctopus.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Straken aka Doctopus.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:55:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gold-leaf]]></title><description><![CDATA[An elf who acts as the official Selesnia envoy to the Expedition Corp. Interested in peaceful creatures and plants brought back from other worlds. Will buy and sell interesting creatures that have been brought to her.]]></description><link>npcs/gold-leaf.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Gold-leaf.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:54:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mephisto]]></title><description><![CDATA[A demon who serves Rakdos. Is the current master of ceremonies for the cult and attached to the REC. Interested in tales (usually involving bloodshed) from other planes.]]></description><link>npcs/mephisto.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Mephisto.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:50:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Isham]]></title><description><![CDATA[A gnome who was an accountant for the Orzhov. Is now the quartermaster for the Expedition Corps. He has officially left the Orzhov to serve Niv-Mizzet Directly. Always seen carrying his quill and with ink on his hands. ]]></description><link>npcs/isham.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Isham.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:48:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lionel]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Leonin who trained to be a hero under Ajani and came to Ravnica with him. Saw Niv-Mizzet’s rebirth and swore his allegiance to him. Acts as leader of the Expedition Corps.]]></description><link>npcs/lionel.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Lionel.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:45:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Doctor Magnificent]]></title><description><![CDATA[A goblin with wild hair. Was experimenting with the firemind while Niv-Mizzet was dead and it was in a weakened state. Was actively attuned to it when Niv-Mizzet was reborn and is now the second smartest creature on the plane. His mind cannot hold all of the knowledge he was shown and thus he is stark raving mad. Works for the Expedition Corps studying artifacts from other worlds. Guild affiliation Izzet.]]></description><link>npcs/doctor-magnificent.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Doctor Magnificent.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:43:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shiss]]></title><description><![CDATA[A humanoid with a raspy voice, always wears a long cloak and a deep hood. Careful inspection will result in characters noticing that the limbs don’t quite move right under the cloak and that occasionally scales can be seen poking out on exposed flesh. Works for the Expedition Corps as an official liaison to all guilds. Effectively the guild job board / drop off.]]></description><link>npcs/shiss.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Shiss.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:41:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Setting details]]></title><description><![CDATA[Welcome to <a data-href="Ravnica" href="ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>, the plane of guilds! If you have lived here for a while forgive me but we have a lot of newcomers these days so let me start by setting the scene. Here on Ravnica we expanded our glorious city until it covered the entire world! As you can imagine having a world spanning city means there's a lot of different ideas and peoples that all have to live together here on Ravnica. You can thank the guild pact for keeping the peace here. Once upon a time we didn't have one and the whole world was in chaos. But that was over 10,000 years ago! More recently we didn't have one again but through some magic that's a bit over my head the guild pact was restored now as a mortal man named Jace Beleren. With peace restored at least while Jace was on Ravnica the city returned to its normal state for the last 20 years or so. Then we were invaded by fucking blue alien zombie hippos pulling chariots for blue fucking alien zombies!!! The history books have taken to calling that event the war of the spark. We lost many Ravnicans during those dark days. The entire plane was a war zone, and when a Ravnican died they just got raised as a zombie to help the invaders. Eventually with the help of many Planeswalkers, who were temporarily trapped here, Niv-Mizzet awoke as the avatar of the plane, the new living guild pact, a dragon, and a god. With this newfound power the invaders were defeated. With the average Ravnican now aware that our world is simply one of many in an infinite cosmos there was a public outcry to learn more about other worlds.It's been 5 years since the war of the spark ended. And we are proud to announce that at long last the Ravnica Expedition Corp is opening general recruitment! We have been sending Ravnicans out into the multiverse since the war of the spark to recruit powerful allies and learn all about the various cultures of the other planes! But now we have perfected the very technology that was once our ruin the Planar Bridge is now the Planar Gate. Before it could only move non-living matter across planar boundaries, but now that the fire mind has had an opportunity to study it, and enough goblins have been tossed in as experiments. We can confidently say that it is a safe and effective way to travel. The Ravnica Expedition Corp is special joint venture between all the guilds under the direct control of Niv-Mizzet himself. Join us here at the Ravnica Expedition Corp and see the worlds! Do you have what it takes to become one of Ravnica's best?]]></description><link>setting-details.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Setting details.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:32:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Character Creation]]></title><description><![CDATA[It is a dawning of a new day in the multiverse. As powers that have been long separated now collide new legends are growing. Will you join their ranks? Will your story remember you as a hero or as a villain?The endgame of this campaign has fights with literal gods and players will have the option to undergo <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Demi-god Transformations" data-href="Demi-god Transformations" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">demi-god transformations</a>. There are other <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#lich_grimhollowpg24,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:transformation=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#lich_grimhollowpg24,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:transformation=1" target="_self">avenues to power</a> that players should consider if they do not want to rely on the gods.<br>The campaign <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Setting details" data-href="Setting details" href="setting-details.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">begins</a> with a group of level one characters on the plane of <a data-href="Ravnica" href="ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>. Player Characters may belong to any guild (no renown) or be guild-less. All Player Characters are fresh recruits to the newly formed Ravnica Expedition Corp (no renown). While this story is set on Ravnica players are not allowed to play as a planeswalker. The reason for this is simple planeswalkers are really hard to balance D&amp;D around. If you want to play a planeswalker may I introduce you to a sister game of D&amp;D called Magic the Gathering where the tagline for over a decade has been "You are a Planeswalker!" If you are dead set on playing as one talk to the DM to home-brew a transformation. <br>Player Characters may be of any race and class in the <a data-href="Approved Material" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Approved Material</a> if you wish to play something outside of that seek DM approval. This is one of the most high fantasy campaigns imaginable. Your race will probably be approved, classes from other sources including home-brew are probably fine but the DM reserves the right to re-balance with the player as needed. This campaign uses a modified set of rules for Character creation: Origin feats may be replaced with any feat that the character meets the requirements for IF AND ONLY IF the character is created above level one. <br>
Everyone is allowed a <a data-href="Signature Magical Item" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Signature Magical Item</a>. Starting magical items are restricted to uncommon items that DO NOT have +1, +2, or +3 in their descriptions. If you want to select the endgame version of the magic item you want the DM will work with you to home-brew a starting version. <br>
If you would like to have an innate boon instead of a Signature Magical Item look over <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#anvilwrought_mot,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:supernatural%20gift=1,flopfeature%20type:extend" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#anvilwrought_mot,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:supernatural%20gift=1,flopfeature%20type:extend" target="_self">Supernatural Gifts.</a> Just like your Signature Magical Item these Gifts can evolve with you over time. Work with the dungeon master to create what you want. <br>
You may use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#pointbuy" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#pointbuy" target="_self">Point Buy</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#array" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#array" target="_self">Standard Array</a>, or a variant on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://statroller.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://statroller.com/" target="_self">4d6dl1</a> for generating Ability Scores. The variant rule for 4d6dl1 is easy for each die you roll you may use the dice as rolled or 3 players choice. This caps the lower bound of each stat to 9. Unless you specifically want to role play with lower stats. Players are allowed, and encouraged, to have and play multiple characters. This used to be the norm. 5e players strayed from this when a group not going to name any names cough Critical Role cough gained a lot of popularity. By the way I love Critical Role I own two of their books and think Matt Mercer and Brennan Lee Mulligan are some of the best DMs of all time ... I still think Vox Machina, Acquisitions Incorporated, and the Mighty Nein are a large component in this shift in thinking especially amongst new players. <br>If running multiple characters becomes problematic (disrupts the flow of play) the DM reserves the right to temporarily demote a secondary character to a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#expert%20sidekick_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1~valdagunslinger=1,flstmiscellaneous:sidekick=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#expert%20sidekick_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1~valdagunslinger=1,flstmiscellaneous:sidekick=1" target="_self">SideKick</a> for the sake of streamlining play. If you would like to make one of your extra characters a sidekick by default that's fine. Some of the most fun I ever had was playing a Dark Elf Cleric with an int of 6 with a conman Aarakocra Expert Sidekick with a cha of 20 manipulating him. Should the main character die and you wish to rework a "permanent sidekick" into a main class that will be allowed.Players can expect to have access to true resurrection magic (for a price). So death is not necessarily the end of a character story. However the juice might not be worth the squeeze (I'm just putting this in writing so that no one thinks I'm changing the rules when I make access to this really hard). <br>Not strictly required but <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#xphb,2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#xphb,2" target="_self">RTFM</a>
<br>Envision who you want to play. A mighty warrior, a powerful mage, a seductive bard, or something more concrete <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://wiki.leagueoflegends.com/en-us/Miss_Fortune" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://wiki.leagueoflegends.com/en-us/Miss_Fortune" target="_self">Miss Fortune,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Drizzt_Do%27Urden" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Drizzt_Do%27Urden" target="_self">Drizzt Do'Urden,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://elderscrolls.fandom.com/wiki/Last_Dragonborn" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://elderscrolls.fandom.com/wiki/Last_Dragonborn" target="_self">The Dovahkiin,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://kingdomhearts.fandom.com/wiki/Mickey_Mouse" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://kingdomhearts.fandom.com/wiki/Mickey_Mouse" target="_self">Mickey Mouse</a> it doesn't matter who or what you pick this is make believe so we can make it happen.
Make them your own. This isn't the DM's story ... and it isn't your's alone. D&amp;D is a collaborative story telling game. Think about how your character fits into the world.
<br>Choose a Class. If you want to keep your life simple pick from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#artificer_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1,flstmiscellaneous:" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#artificer_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1,flstmiscellaneous:" target="_self">this list</a> if you're not afraid of the truth <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#fighter_phb,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1,flstmiscellaneous:" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#fighter_phb,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1,flstmiscellaneous:" target="_self">this list</a>. For total creative freedom ... work with the DM to get your degenerate broken home-brew approved.
<br>Choose a Race (or for the new books Species). Don't get overwhelmed just pick one and move on. You can use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#giff_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~egw=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~aag=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~phb=1~ftd=1~scag=1~wbtw=1~scc=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#giff_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~egw=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~aag=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~phb=1~ftd=1~scag=1~wbtw=1~scc=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1" target="_self">this list</a> for basics. You can use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#plasmoid_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~eepc=1~egw=1~mpmm=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~psk=1~aag=1~psa=1~psd=1~lfl=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~abh=1~vrgr=1~phb=1~ftd=1~mtf=1~scag=1~psz=1~wbtw=1~psx=1~awm=1~idrotf=1~oga=1~psi=1~dsotdq=1~lr=1~scc=1~ttp=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~oneshotwondersholidaypack=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#plasmoid_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~eepc=1~egw=1~mpmm=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~psk=1~aag=1~psa=1~psd=1~lfl=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~abh=1~vrgr=1~phb=1~ftd=1~mtf=1~scag=1~psz=1~wbtw=1~psx=1~awm=1~idrotf=1~oga=1~psi=1~dsotdq=1~lr=1~scc=1~ttp=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~oneshotwondersholidaypack=1" target="_self">this list</a> if you are as depraved as the DM. Again for total creative freedom ... work with the DM to get your overpowered furry OC home-brew approved.
Roll some mother fucking dice! Also known as Get your Ability Scores. Generate your abilities scores with any method mentioned above. Rolls must be made in front of the DM. There is a secret 4th option from older editions no one talks about any more. It's roll 1d20 per score. I'll let you choose this one if you want. But no grace rolls or taking averages. You are stuck with what you get.
Pick an Alignment. This is a stupid and outdated set of mechanics. Our first two steps replace this.
Work with the DM to get your backstory approved. This is the most important part of making your Character come to life in the world. You know who you want to play from the first two steps. Now you work with the DM to integrate them into the larger story. After this step you should no longer be your characters biggest fan. The game is more fun when you make the DM the biggest fan of your character. When the DM roots for the party to win you get away with more dope shit at the table.
Select your Signature Magic Item with DM approval. Copy a bunch of shit down from the books onto your character sheet. This is the part that sucks the most but without it your character doesn't exist. It's not that bad at level one and when you level up normally you get lots of downtime to repeat this step copying down your new abilities. Get used to it now if you struggle the DM will help you but as the campaign goes on you should want to be able to do this yourself.
Have a snack! Grab a drink! Get one of each for you DM! Enjoy watching your fellow party members come to life in a similar way.
]]></description><link>character-creation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Character Creation.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 23:17:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[Welcome to the lore for Fey of Ravnica!You might want any of these<a data-href="Character Creation" href="character-creation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Character Creation</a><br>
<a data-href="Setting details" href="setting-details.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Setting details</a><br>
<a data-href="Ravnica" href="ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 22:33:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ravnica]]></title><description><![CDATA[If you want to know way more about Ravnica than you need to read <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr" target="_self">this.</a> If you keep reading that whole book you'll know more than the DM does.]]></description><link>ravnica.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Ravnica.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:26:34 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>