<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Fey of Ravnica]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Fey of Ravnica</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 15:10:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 15:10:27 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Variant Rules]]></title><description><![CDATA[We are using the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://openlegendrpg.com/core-rules/introduction" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://openlegendrpg.com/core-rules/introduction" target="_self">Open Legend</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://openlegendrpg.com/core-rules/wealth-equipment" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://openlegendrpg.com/core-rules/wealth-equipment" target="_self">wealth system.</a><br>I still haven't been able to write down the words to describe how my crafting system works. I don't want to take money from a table top game system so I'm not going to post their rules but players can ask me for a copy of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://sonofoak.com/pages/what-is-the-mist-engine" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://sonofoak.com/pages/what-is-the-mist-engine" target="_self">Legend In The Mist by Son Of Oak</a> while not exactly how I run crafting their tag system is very close. There are other systems that will be involved while on other planes.I am open to adding more that players are interested in.]]></description><link>mechanics/variant-rules.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Mechanics/Variant Rules.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:43:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Get RID of these Cultists!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Get RID of these Cultists!There appears to be some kind of new cult here on Ravnica. I was working my stall at the market last week, when suddenly someone shouted something, then two lunatics drew swords out of nowhere and started battling to the death. Disrupting the peace making it hard for a local business woman to ply her craft. I already talked to the Rakdos troupe to see if it was them. While they said "we like their style" they said it wasn't them. And you know if it was, they'd claim it. if these people are operating outside of a guild and disturbing the peace that violates the Guild Pact. Somebody needs to track down this new cult and put an end to them.I pay my taxes so why should I offer a reward? Do your job!
Client has declined to offer a rewardI don't want to waste real manpower on this ...This quest is locked to New Recruits! Prove yourself on the home front before we toss you among the stars!Okay listen up. I know this isn't what you signed up for. Half of you want to see other worlds and the other half just want to kill blue zombies for revenge. But Ravnica is our home and I will let no one threaten it. Go to the market undercover and capture at least one of these cultist alive. Keep the collateral damage to a minimum or its coming out of your paychecks! After you subdue one of these freaks bring them back here, the REC will handle the interrogation.
-- Lionel Commander of the Corp]]></description><link>job-board/get-rid-of-these-cultists!.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Job Board/Get RID of these Cultists!.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:18:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Signature Magical Item]]></title><description><![CDATA[I love magic items! Classes only get you so far in D&amp;D so much power and creativity is handed to players when you give them a magic item. So many insane stories come from players using a magic item in a way the DM didn't imagine. One of the greatest of all times has to be <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C2SAkGjgZSY" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C2SAkGjgZSY" target="_self">Jester offering a Hag a cupcake</a>.While I will give you access to many magical items throughout the course of the campaign I like to give players a magical item that grows with them. This does two things. First its another way for you to direct your character's narrative and second it gives me as the DM a parallel way to offer character power advancement without just leveling you up.There is no cap on how strong these can get. By the end you can be rocking a Artifact that you designed throughout the whole campaign. However at the until you are level three they cannot give a flat +1, +2, or +3.]]></description><link>mechanics/signature-magical-item.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Mechanics/Signature Magical Item.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:43:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Approved Material]]></title><description><![CDATA[Click this for the version your DM is using <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/index.html#blankhash,loadexthomebrew:pugilist2024~dungeondadstatblocks~grimhollowpg24~scoc~bloodhunter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/index.html#blankhash,loadexthomebrew:pugilist2024~dungeondadstatblocks~grimhollowpg24~scoc~bloodhunter" target="_self">5e.tools</a>Detailed Breakdown:
Any 5e core rule book including Adventure settings and all of Planeshift. Critical Role's Bloodhunter Class
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#grimhollowpg24" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#grimhollowpg24" target="_self">Grim Hollow: Player's Guide 2024</a>
<br>D&amp;D Beyond's: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#pugilist2024" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#pugilist2024" target="_self">Pugilist Class</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#scoc" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#scoc" target="_self">Stibbles Codex of Companions</a>
I am currently open to more.
]]></description><link>mechanics/approved-material.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Mechanics/Approved Material.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:40:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Character Creation]]></title><description><![CDATA[It is a dawning of a new day in the multiverse. As powers that have been long separated now collide new legends are growing. Will you join their ranks? Will your story remember you as a hero or as a villain?The endgame of this campaign has fights with literal gods and players will have the option to undergo <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Demi-god Transformations" data-href="Demi-god Transformations" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">demi-god transformations</a>. There are other <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#lich_grimhollowpg24,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:transformation=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#lich_grimhollowpg24,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:transformation=1" target="_self">avenues to power</a> that players should consider if they do not want to rely on the gods.<br>The campaign <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Setting details" data-href="Setting details" href="setting/setting-details.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">begins</a> with a group of level one characters on the plane of <a data-href="Ravnica" href="setting/ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>. Player Characters may belong to any guild (no renown) or be guild-less. All Player Characters are fresh recruits to the newly formed Ravnica Expedition Corp (no renown). While this story is set on Ravnica players are not allowed to play as a planeswalker. The reason for this is simple planeswalkers are really hard to balance D&amp;D around. If you want to play a planeswalker may I introduce you to a sister game of D&amp;D called Magic the Gathering where the tagline for over a decade has been "You are a Planeswalker!" If you are dead set on playing as one talk to the DM to home-brew a transformation. <br>Player Characters may be of any race and class in the <a data-href="Approved Material" href="mechanics/approved-material.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Approved Material</a> if you wish to play something outside of that seek DM approval. This is one of the most high fantasy campaigns imaginable. Your race will probably be approved, classes from other sources including home-brew are probably fine but the DM reserves the right to re-balance with the player as needed. This campaign uses a modified set of rules for Character creation: Origin feats may be replaced with any feat that the character meets the requirements for IF AND ONLY IF the character is created above level one. <br>
Everyone is allowed a <a data-href="Signature Magical Item" href="mechanics/signature-magical-item.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Signature Magical Item</a>. Starting magical items are restricted to uncommon items that DO NOT have +1, +2, or +3 in their descriptions. If you want to select the endgame version of the magic item you want the DM will work with you to home-brew a starting version. <br>
If you would like to have an innate boon instead of a Signature Magical Item look over <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#anvilwrought_mot,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:supernatural%20gift=1,flopfeature%20type:extend" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/charcreationoptions.html#anvilwrought_mot,fbmt:sand~b1~b0~b0,flstfeature%20type:supernatural%20gift=1,flopfeature%20type:extend" target="_self">Supernatural Gifts.</a> Just like your Signature Magical Item these Gifts can evolve with you over time. Work with the dungeon master to create what you want. <br>
You may use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#pointbuy" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#pointbuy" target="_self">Point Buy</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#array" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/statgen.html#array" target="_self">Standard Array</a>, or a variant on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://statroller.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://statroller.com/" target="_self">4d6dl1</a> for generating Ability Scores. The variant rule for 4d6dl1 is easy for each die you roll you may use the dice as rolled or 3 players choice. This caps the lower bound of each stat to 9. Unless you specifically want to role play with lower stats. Players are allowed, and encouraged, to have and play as multiple characters. This used to be very normal although it has fallen out of favor with most 5e players. For the first few sessions I will be limiting you to playing one character at a time to streamline play. After that I will open this up for you. Multiple characters allows for a lot more interesting play options at the table. Suddenly things like splitting the party aren't nearly as big of an issue. The DM can always scale the difficultly of encounters when the party splits so the real reason that parties are told to avoid it is that its boring for Players when they are off screen for an extended period, having multiple character fixes this because you just send one of your characters with each group. As a Player you also dramatically expand your options in the story. Barbarians are great super fun, definitely in the top 15 of available classes, but they can start to feel pointless when there is nothing to rage at and smash. Bard's are great in social situations and you can make them great in combat but outside of combat is where they shine. If you are playing both of them at the same time you actually get to min-max without min-maxing. Instead of focusing on how do I make this character the best I can for their mechanical role in the party, you get to relax a little and do stupid things like put all your points into strength on the barbarian because you know the bard is going to send a lot of heals your way in combat. And then out of combat you still can have more dynamic engagement with the plot than "Grok hit tiny man?" which you know is hysterical for at least the first 1,000 times you say it but eventually it gets overplayed. If the thought of running two full blown characters sounds like way too much to handle, I get it. It really can be a lot to think about at the table. But you can do it I know you can because the DM does it with many characters every session. If you are still intimidated remember that you are encouraged but not required to have multiple characters. <br>Also last thought on the matter <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#expert%20sidekick_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1~valdagunslinger=1,flstmiscellaneous:sidekick=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#expert%20sidekick_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1~pugilist2024=1~valdagunslinger=1,flstmiscellaneous:sidekick=1" target="_self">SideKicks</a> exist. They are dramatically simplified characters which can make a good starting point to playing multiple characters. Some of the most fun I ever had was playing a Dark Elf Cleric with an int of 6 with a conman Aarakocra Expert Sidekick with a cha of 20 manipulating him. At least one of those characters shows up in this campaign :) Should the main character die and you wish to rework a sidekick into a main class that will be allowed.Players can expect to have access to true resurrection magic (for a price). So death is not necessarily the end of a character story. However the juice might not be worth the squeeze (I'm just putting this in writing so that no one thinks I'm changing the rules when I make access to this really hard). <br>Not strictly required but <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#xphb,2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#xphb,2" target="_self">RTFM</a>
<br>Envision who you want to play. A mighty warrior, a powerful mage, a seductive bard, or something more concrete <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://wiki.leagueoflegends.com/en-us/Miss_Fortune" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://wiki.leagueoflegends.com/en-us/Miss_Fortune" target="_self">Miss Fortune,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Drizzt_Do%27Urden" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Drizzt_Do%27Urden" target="_self">Drizzt Do'Urden,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://elderscrolls.fandom.com/wiki/Last_Dragonborn" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://elderscrolls.fandom.com/wiki/Last_Dragonborn" target="_self">The Dovahkiin,</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://kingdomhearts.fandom.com/wiki/Mickey_Mouse" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://kingdomhearts.fandom.com/wiki/Mickey_Mouse" target="_self">Mickey Mouse</a> it doesn't matter who or what you pick this is make believe so we can make it happen.
Make them your own. This isn't the DM's story ... and it isn't your's alone. D&amp;D is a collaborative story telling game. Think about how your character fits into the world.
<br>Choose a Class. If you want to keep your life simple pick from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#artificer_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1,flstmiscellaneous:" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#artificer_tce,fbmt:sand~b0~b0~b0,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~lordtob=1~humblewoodcampaignsetting=1~grimhollowpg24=1~humblewoodtales=1,flstmiscellaneous:" target="_self">this list</a> if you're not afraid of the truth <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/classes.html#blood%20hunter_bloodhunter,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~grimhollowpg24=1~pugilist2024=1~bloodhunter=1,flstmiscellaneous:" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/classes.html#blood%20hunter_bloodhunter,flstsource:tce=1~erlw=1~efa=1~phb=1~scag=1~xge=1~bgg=1~xphb=1~mot=1~vrgr=1~frhof=1~dmg=1~psa=1~ggr=1~egw=1~ftd=1~uathemysticclass=1~psk=1~dsotdq=1~grimhollowpg24=1~pugilist2024=1~bloodhunter=1,flstmiscellaneous:" target="_self">this list</a>. For total creative freedom ... work with the DM to get your degenerate broken home-brew approved.
<br>Choose a Race (or for the new books Species). Don't get overwhelmed just pick one and move on. You can use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#giff_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~egw=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~aag=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~phb=1~ftd=1~scag=1~wbtw=1~scc=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#giff_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~egw=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~aag=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~phb=1~ftd=1~scag=1~wbtw=1~scc=1~ai=1~grimhollowpg24=1" target="_self">this list</a> for basics. You can use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#plasmoid_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~eepc=1~egw=1~mpmm=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~psk=1~aag=1~psa=1~psd=1~lfl=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~abh=1~vrgr=1~phb=1~ftd=1~mtf=1~scag=1~psz=1~wbtw=1~psx=1~awm=1~idrotf=1~oga=1~psi=1~dsotdq=1~lr=1~scc=1~ttp=1~ai=1~dungeondadstatblocks=1~grimhollowpg24=1,flstmiscellaneous:" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#plasmoid_aag,flstsource:dmg=1~eepc=1~egw=1~mpmm=1~vgm=1~xphb=1~psk=1~aag=1~psa=1~psd=1~lfl=1~erlw=1~ggr=1~mot=1~efa=1~tce=1~abh=1~vrgr=1~phb=1~ftd=1~mtf=1~scag=1~psz=1~wbtw=1~psx=1~awm=1~idrotf=1~oga=1~psi=1~dsotdq=1~lr=1~scc=1~ttp=1~ai=1~dungeondadstatblocks=1~grimhollowpg24=1,flstmiscellaneous:" target="_self">this list</a> if you are as depraved as the DM. Again for total creative freedom ... work with the DM to get your overpowered furry OC home-brew approved.
Roll some mother fucking dice! Also known as Get your Ability Scores. Generate your abilities scores with any method mentioned above. Rolls must be made in front of the DM. There is a secret 4th option from older editions no one talks about any more. It's roll 1d20 per score. I'll let you choose this one if you want. But no grace rolls or taking averages. You are stuck with what you get. Technically 1d20 can let you start with a 19 or 20 in a stat where as the max elsewhere is 18 ... but statistically 4d6dl1 is the best and my variant on it only makes it better.
Pick an Alignment. This is a stupid and outdated set of mechanics. Our first two steps replace this.
Work with the DM to get your backstory approved. This is the most important part of making your Character come to life in the world. You know who you want to play from the first two steps. Now you work with the DM to integrate them into the larger story. After this step you should no longer be your character's biggest fan. The game is more fun when you make the DM the biggest fan of your character. When the DM roots for the party to win you get away with more dope shit at the table.
Select your Signature Magic Item with DM approval. MATH TIME!!! WOOOOO!!!! It kinda sucks ... but its really not that hard its mostly just adding a few single digit numbers together. The DM will show you the easy way to copy everything else you need on your character sheet without having to write it down. But the numbers are important for you to get familiar with so you have to copy those yourself.
Have a snack! Grab a drink! Get one of each for you DM! Enjoy watching your fellow party members come to life in a similar way.
]]></description><link>mechanics/character-creation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Mechanics/Character Creation.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:34:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Setting details]]></title><description><![CDATA[Welcome to <a data-href="Ravnica" href="setting/ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>, the plane of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Guild Primer" data-href="Guild Primer" href="guilds/guild-primer.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">guilds</a>! If you have lived here for a while forgive me but we have a lot of newcomers these days so let me start by setting the scene. Here on Ravnica we expanded our glorious city until it covered the entire world! As you can imagine having a world spanning city means there's a lot of different ideas and peoples that all have to live together here on Ravnica. You can thank the guild pact for keeping the peace here. Once upon a time we didn't have one and the whole world was in chaos. But that was over 10,000 years ago! More recently we didn't have one again but through some magic that's a bit over my head the guild pact was restored now as a mortal man named <a data-href="Jace Beleren" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jace Beleren</a>. With peace restored at least while Jace was on Ravnica the city returned more or less to its normal state for the last 20 years or so. <br>Then we were invaded by fucking blue alien zombie hippos pulling chariots for blue fucking alien zombies!!! The history books have taken to calling that event the war of the spark. We lost many Ravnicans during those dark days. The entire plane was a war zone, and when a Ravnican died they just got raised as a zombie to help the invaders. Eventually with the help of many Planeswalkers, who were temporarily trapped here, <a data-href="Niv-Mizzet" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Niv-Mizzet</a> awoke as the avatar of the plane, the new living guild pact, a dragon, and a god. With this newfound power the invaders were defeated. With the average Ravnican now aware that our world is simply one of many in an infinite cosmos there was a public outcry to learn more about other worlds.<br>It's been 5 years since the war of the spark ended. And we are proud to announce that at long last the <a data-href="Ravnica Expedition Corp" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica Expedition Corp</a> is opening general recruitment! We have been sending Ravnicans out into the multiverse since the war of the spark to recruit powerful allies and learn all about the various cultures of the other planes! But now we have perfected the very technology that was once our ruin the Planar Bridge is now the Planar Gate. Before it could only move non-living matter across planar boundaries, but now that the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Firemind" data-href="Firemind" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">fire mind</a> has had an opportunity to study it, and enough goblins have been tossed in as experiments. We can confidently say that it is a safe and effective way to travel. The Ravnica Expedition Corp is special joint venture between all the guilds under the direct control of Niv-Mizzet himself. Join us here at the Ravnica Expedition Corp and see the worlds! Do you have what it takes to become one of Ravnica's best?]]></description><link>setting/setting-details.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Setting/Setting details.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:26:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Twinless]]></title><description><![CDATA[A <a data-href="lazotep" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">lazotep</a> covered <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#khenra_psa" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#khenra_psa" target="_self">Jackal</a> zombie. Part of <a data-href="Nicol Bolas" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nicol Bolas</a>’ invasion force died in the invasion. Was brought back by <a data-href="Lillianna" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Lillianna</a> more times than any other. Revived by the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Golgari Swarm" data-href="Golgari Swarm" href="guilds/golgari-swarm.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Golgari</a> for them to study the necromancy of other worlds. Official envoy of the Golgari to the Expedition Corps.]]></description><link>npcs/twinless.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Twinless.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:50:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Straken]]></title><description><![CDATA[A humanoid with feathers and scales. A <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Simic Combine" data-href="Simic Combine" href="guilds/simic-combine.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Simic</a> researcher working with the <a data-href="Expedition Corps" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Expedition Corps</a> to study xenobiology. Also under direct orders from <a data-href="Niv-Mizzet" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Niv-Mizzet</a> to study <a data-href="Doctor Magnificent" href="npcs/doctor-magnificent.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Doctor Magnificent</a> and the effects the <a data-href="Firemind" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Firemind</a> exposure had on him. <a data-href="Doctor Magnificent" href="npcs/doctor-magnificent.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Doctor Magnificent</a> is the one who gave her the unfortunate moniker of Doctopus.]]></description><link>npcs/straken.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Straken.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:49:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mephisto]]></title><description><![CDATA[A demon who serves <a data-href="Rakdos" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rakdos</a>. Is the current master of ceremonies for the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Cult of Rakdos" data-href="Cult of Rakdos" href="guilds/cult-of-rakdos.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">cult</a> and attached to the REC. Interested in tales (usually involving bloodshed) from other planes.]]></description><link>npcs/mephisto.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Mephisto.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:47:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lionel]]></title><description><![CDATA[A <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#leonin_mot" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#leonin_mot" target="_self">Leonin</a> who trained to be a hero under <a data-href="Ajani" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ajani</a> and came to <a data-href="Ravnica" href="setting/ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a> with him. Saw <a data-href="Niv-Mizzet" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Niv-Mizzet</a>’s rebirth and swore his allegiance to him. Acts as leader of the Expedition Corps.]]></description><link>npcs/lionel.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Lionel.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:46:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Isham]]></title><description><![CDATA[A gnome who was an accountant for the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Orzhov Syndicate" data-href="Orzhov Syndicate" href="guilds/orzhov-syndicate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Orzhov</a>. Is now the quartermaster for the Expedition Corps. He has officially left the Orzhov to serve <a data-href="Niv-Mizzet" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Niv-Mizzet</a> Directly. Always seen carrying his quill and with ink on his hands. ]]></description><link>npcs/isham.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Isham.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:45:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Grug]]></title><description><![CDATA[An orc who wears nothing but a loincloth. A <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Gruul Clans" data-href="Gruul Clans" href="guilds/gruul-clans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gruul</a> beast master for the Expedition Corps. Helps tame rampaging monsters brought through the planar portal. Keeps a menagerie of fierce beasts to train Corps members against to help prepare them for the rigors of planar travel.]]></description><link>npcs/grug.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Grug.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:45:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gold-leaf]]></title><description><![CDATA[An elf who acts as the official <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Selesnya Conclave" data-href="Selesnya Conclave" href="guilds/selesnya-conclave.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Selesnya</a> envoy to the Expedition Corp. Interested in peaceful creatures and plants brought back from other worlds. Will buy and sell interesting creatures that have been brought to her.]]></description><link>npcs/gold-leaf.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Gold-leaf.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:44:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Doctor Magnificent]]></title><description><![CDATA[A goblin with wild hair. Was experimenting with the <a data-href="Firemind" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Firemind</a> while <a data-href="Niv-Mizzet" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Niv-Mizzet</a> was dead and it was in a weakened state. Was actively attuned to it when Niv-Mizzet was reborn and is now the second smartest creature on the plane. His mind cannot hold all of the knowledge he was shown and thus he is stark raving mad. Works for the Expedition Corps studying artifacts from other worlds. Acts as the Guild contact for the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Izzet League" data-href="Izzet League" href="guilds/izzet-league.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Izzet</a>]]></description><link>npcs/doctor-magnificent.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Doctor Magnificent.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:43:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Casper]]></title><description><![CDATA[A ghost who acts as the official envoy of the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Orzhov Syndicate" data-href="Orzhov Syndicate" href="guilds/orzhov-syndicate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Orzhov</a> guild to the REC. Is in charge of payroll for the Corp and is willing to offer loans to characters.]]></description><link>npcs/casper.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Casper.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:42:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shiss]]></title><description><![CDATA[A humanoid with a raspy voice, always wears a long cloak and a deep hood. Careful inspection will result in characters noticing that the limbs don’t quite move right under the cloak and that occasionally scales can be seen poking out on exposed flesh. Works for the Expedition Corps as an official liaison to all guilds. Effectively the guild job board / drop off.]]></description><link>npcs/shiss.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Shiss.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:42:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rank and File]]></title><description><![CDATA[A <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#loxodon_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#loxodon_ggr" target="_self">Loxodon</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/races.html#minotaur_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/races.html#minotaur_ggr" target="_self">Rhox</a> who act as the official envoys of the <a data-href="Boros Legion" href="guilds/boros-legion.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Boros Legion</a> to the Expedition Corps. Offer training and additional manpower for expeditions as well as interested in any fresh recruits that can be brought back from a mission.]]></description><link>npcs/rank-and-file.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Rank and File.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:41:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Justice]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Vedalken who serves as the official envoy of the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Azorius Senate" data-href="Azorius Senate" href="guilds/azorius-senate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Azorius</a> to the Expedition Corps. Was previously an enforcer, was promoted to judge the day before the invasion. Interested in the laws, customs, and history of other worlds.]]></description><link>npcs/justice.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">NPCs/Justice.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:40:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Selesnya Conclave]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/052-237.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Winona Nelson" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/052-237.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/052-237.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Winona Nelson<br>“Selesnya troops poured into the streets, emptying the nature temples, wildlife preserves, and other green spaces controlled by the conclave. The centaurs' hooves clattered on the cobblestones and the wolf-riders bounded over stone bridges. Human and elf infantry flooded through the arteries of the district, streaming past intersections and flowing around buildings. Griffons and their riders swooped down out of a blanket of low clouds, strafing past the spires. Emmara rode on the shoulder of a massive creature made of a snarl of marble, wood, and vines, her hand resting on its great head. Two more of the nature behemoths strode ahead of her, swinging their limbs in slow motion, indenting the streets with their footfalls as the other Selesnya troops ran between their legs. Below her, Captain Calomir led the Selesnya army. He rode his white war rhino, driving the Selesnya ranks forward, guiding them through the streets toward the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;horde.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistLike a thriving garden, carefully tended and abundantly fertile, the communities of the Selesnya Conclave are a harmonious union of nature and civilization. The members of the conclave dream of embracing all of Ravnica in their peaceful union. In the meantime, they are growing an army, preparing to resist the ambition and destructive impulses of the other guilds and fight to defend their way of life.<br>At the heart of the Selesnya faith and philosophy is the Worldsoul, called Mat'Selesnya, which its devotees believe to be a manifestation of nature itself. At the signing of the original Guildpact, Mat'Selesnya was embodied in an elemental form and acted as the guild's first guildmaster. The current guildmaster,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" target="_self">Trostani</a>—three dryads fused together with Mat'Selesnya into a single being—is said to embody the will of the Worldsoul in a similar way. The original mission of the conclave involved conservation and charity, but its focus has long been on expanding its community, in which all members are cared for and nature is preserved in harmony with civilization.The Selesnya Conclave is organized into enclaves called vernadi, which are communes built around central trees. The vernadi are smaller versions of the guildhall, the great city-tree Vitu-Ghazi. A dryad, called a voda, is called forth from that central tree to be the leader of the community, connecting the vernadi and its devotees to the Worldsoul and uniting them with the will of the entire conclave.<br>A voda is accessible to all the guild members in her care. You have regular contact with your voda, who knows your name and has a good idea of your interests, goals, and strengths. And since your voda is mystically linked to the guildmaster,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" target="_self">Trostani</a>, through communion with the Worldsoul, it's safe to assume that&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#trostani_ggr" target="_self">Trostani</a>&nbsp;knows who you are as well.In addition to the voda, military and religious leaders in each vernadi regularly communicate with its members. Ordinary members of the conclave spend a few hours every day training with a military instructor and studying with a religious teacher.Despite the growing tensions that now grip the world, in the long view of the Selesnya Conclave, not much has changed. Ravnica is troubled, but Ravnica has always been troubled. The Living Guildpact is absent, but the Guildpact comes and goes. The Worldsoul has not changed, nor has the will of Mat'Selesnya: the conclave's main goal is to grow, as it has always been. Its strength lies in its numbers.The conclave clings to the ideal of a peaceful collective in which individual desires are subordinate to the good of the whole group. The guild wants to see this beloved community grow, flourish, and thrive in peace. But as much as it values peace within the community, it displays incredible ferocity when that harmony is threatened.Selesnya's vision is centered on the idea of harmony between civilization and nature. To advance the cause of civilized society, the conclave believes in the need for an ordered structure that orients the group toward the pursuit of the common good. At the same time, the guild's connection with the natural world gives the conclave a fervent appreciation for the interconnectedness of all things. Selesnya doesn't tolerate selfishness or ambition, instead urging its members to put the needs of others ahead of their own desires and to use the power of nature—including nature's wrath—to drive away those whose selfishness threatens the coherence of the group.The greatest danger that Selesnya faces lies in the ambitions of other guilds, which are flourishing in the absence of the Guildpact. Selesnya's way of curbing this grasping selfishness has always been to outnumber the other guilds. Its members aren't naive; they fully realize that the ambitions of other guilds will lead to violence. And they aim to be prepared for that violence when it erupts."For my seedlings to survive," Mat'Selesnya says, "we must grow an army capable of overwhelming such ambitions." Some of that army is literally grown, in the case of plant creatures and elementals. A great many members grow up in the guild from childhood and learn their martial skills at the guild's training grounds. And still more join the guild through recruitment—especially in these troubling times, when rumors of war and a sense of imminent doom make Selesnya's message of harmonious community sound ever more appealing.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,selesnya%20conclave" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,selesnya%20conclave" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/selesnya-conclave.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Selesnya Conclave.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:19:54 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/052-237.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/052-237.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Golgari Swarm]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/028-215.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Milivoj Ćeran" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/028-215.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/028-215.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Milivoj Ćeran“A small crowd of pale elves and humans stepped into the light. Bits of bone and detritus woven into their matted hair clicked lightly. Their chitinous armor swarmed with tiny, riotous insects that moved in and out of the sheen of moss growing on their shoulders—a bed for sprouting fungi. Whether it was the Golgari themselves who had made the chittering sound or their bugs, Ral could not be sure.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistThe teeming masses that compose the Golgari Swarm see themselves as pragmatic above all else, uncowed by the simple fact that death is part of the cycle of life. They believe the idea of life and death as opposing forces to be nothing more than naive sentimentality. They know everything crumbles and rots in the end, and then new life springs from that rot. Time inevitably passes, bringing both destruction and new creation to all things.The original mandate of the Golgari Swarm under the leadership of Svogthir, its Devkarin founder, was to maintain Ravnica's agriculture and manage its waste. But Svogthir's interest in necromancy, and his eventual transformation into a lich, shaped the course of the guild's activities and gave birth to its philosophy of embracing death as part of nature's cycle.<br>The leadership of the Golgari has undergone several major changes, but the nature of the swarm makes it easily adaptable to the churn of continuous cycles. Being alive isn't a prerequisite for leadership, as demonstrated by the rule of the current guildmaster, the elf lich&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#jarad%20vod%20savo_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#jarad%20vod%20savo_ggr" target="_self">Jarad Vod Savo</a>. Assassination is seen as a perfectly valid means of effecting political change, which is how Jarad's sister, Savra, took control of the guild before him. Various groups of people and monsters coexist within the swarm, their relative power waxing and waning with the years, and through it all, the guild goes on.The three most important power groups within the Golgari are the Devkarin elves, the medusas (also called gorgons in Ravnica), and the insectile kraul. Jarad is an undead representative of the Devkarin, so the elves claim a privileged position within the guild for the moment.Members of the Golgari Swarm live in the shadow of Jarad and the leaders of the individual factions. The machinations among elves, medusas, kraul, and other creatures rarely bring any significant improvement to the lives of the swarm's countless members, but often cause disruption and occasionally disaster. Most guild members believe it's best to keep their heads down and stay out of the political conflict and to avoid attracting the disfavor of the Ochran, the guild's order of assassins. More adventurous members might enjoy intrigue and politics, or might unwittingly become tangled up in the schemes of the guild's leaders.Jarad maintains a council of shamans and rogues to serve as a combination of advisory parliament and spy agency. These high chancellors rarely convene publicly, preferring to disperse themselves throughout the swarm to keep information flowing from the nucleus to every part of the organism.The Golgari Swarm celebrates the growth and vibrancy of the natural world, but gives equal attention to nature's facets of destruction, decay, and death. It finds allies and agents in the form of fungi, oozes, insects, diseases, and other unsavory aspects of nature, and it uses the power of nature actively toward the goal of advancing its own place in the world. But the Golgari have also learned patience from nature; they are content to work from the shadows, harnessing the energy that comes from decay while the civilization of Ravnica slowly erodes and destroys itself.The teeming hordes of the Golgari Swarm believe it is finally their time to shine. They have dwelled under the streets and under the sway of the other guilds for too long. They are convinced that Ravnica's institutions are now on the verge of collapse and that the absence of the Living Guildpact proves it. However, the Golgari are neither surprised nor panicked by this, for they believe that all things eventually rot and die, and from this decay, new life blooms. As such, the Golgari see the looming interguild conflict as a necessary final push to bring about a new era—their era.The Golgari are preparing for upheaval. They have sealed many of the passages leading into the undercity, making their territory seem like an impregnable subterranean fortress. Within it, the Golgari domain retains its grandeur, a mysterious and wondrous kingdom. The rare visitors who stumble into it are awed by its beauty and its aura of ancient power. Palatial architecture fills cavernous sewer chambers, and luminescent spores float through the air to shed an otherworldly light on the moss-covered masonry. Entering Golgari territory feels like stepping into a secret world of dangerous beauty.Also called the elves of shadow, the Devkarin are one of the three branches of Ravnica's elf race. Like other elves, the Devkarin are adept spellcasters, counting most of the Golgari's shamans among their number.After being cast out of the nascent Selesnya Conclave millennia ago, the Devkarin found a home amid the corrupted and overgrown places of Ravnica, and the Devkarin necromancer Svogthir became the founder of the Golgari Swarm. Since then, the Devkarin have been a major influence in the guild, even during the times when they didn't hold absolute power. Regardless of who rules the guild, the Devkarin follow the guidance of a high priest, called the matka. The matka's spiritual leadership usually aligns with the guildmaster's temporal commands, but during times when the guild is ruled by a non-elf faction, the matka can be a significant dissenting voice.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/029-216.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Florian de Gesincourt" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/029-216.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/029-216.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Florian de Gesincourt<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,golgari%20swarm" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,golgari%20swarm" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/golgari-swarm.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Golgari Swarm.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:09:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/028-215.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/028-215.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cult of Rakdos]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/046-246.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Sung Choi" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/046-246.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/046-246.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Sung Choi<br>“Jace walked into the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;club, pushing into a wall of scents and sounds. The ceilings were surprisingly high inside, draped with banners and spiked chains. An impish creature hooted as it dangled from a high wire while a man in leather chaps swallowed orbs of fire and breathed them back out through his snaggly teeth. Scarred, black-scaled drakes fought viciously in cages that swung from the ceiling, and the stink of sweat and singed flesh wafted from adjoining alcoves. Against the wall stood an enormous sentry, somewhere along the spectrum between rotund man and compact giant, dressed in what looked like the motley of a harlequin jester crossed with barbed wire.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The Secretist<br>Tomorrow is an illusion; everything is ridiculous. Members of the Cult of Rakdos have witnessed the grandiose speeches and self-important plans of other guilds and concluded that their rivals take themselves far too seriously. Since death comes for everyone, and since order tends inevitably toward chaos, the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;believe that unrestrained, moment-to-moment hedonism is the only sane way to live. Of course, few other Ravnicans would describe the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;as sane.<br>The Cult of Rakdos bears the name of the demon lord who founded it. As laid out in the Guildpact, the guild was intended to fill roles concerning entertainment, mining, and manual labor. Some argue that any effort to give a demonic cult a respectable role in society was doomed to failure, but the cult remains part of Ravnica's social fabric nevertheless. The Guildpact prohibits the cult's extermination, and its entertainments—even as dark and destructive as they are—hold broad appeal. From rowdy mobs who love to see the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;skewer the powerful elites to decadent socialites who come to the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;for illicit amusements, most of Ravnica's people don't really want the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;to go away, as much as they might publicly protest otherwise.<br>As one of Ravnica's original guild founders, the demon&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;has been part of Ravnica for millennia. Members of other guilds know&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;through his reputation for capricious cruelty and megalomania, but those who join the guild idolize him for his magnetic presence, which inspires art and encourages utter wantonness. Because&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;finds destruction entertaining, his cultists incorporate deadly acts into their performances in hopes of catching his eye and earning his favor.<br>Stages for&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;performances appear on streets and plazas throughout Ravnica every night, and they're gone by morning—carried to and from on the backs of giants. Permanent establishments that cater to dark desires are tucked away in the seediest neighborhoods of the city, such as the Smelting Quarter in Precinct Six of the Tenth District.The Cult of Rakdos is centered on a demon lord who exemplifies the concepts of chaos and evil. At its worst, the cult is driven by a lust for power, extreme selfishness, and a lack of compassion. Cultists take delight in causing pain to others to make sure they know their place, which is subservient to the powerful adherents of this self-centered philosophy.The cult's chaotic nature fuels its passion, impulsiveness, and obsession with freedom. A guild of unbridled hedonism, it does what it wants, driven by base desires and a strong streak of cruelty.<br>The Cult of Rakdos was originally recognized as a guild as part of an effort to channel the impulses of demons, giants, ogres, and humans into an acceptable direction. That effort has never been completely successful. Now, as tension builds in Ravnica and several guilds attempt to crack down on chaos and criminal activity, the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;cult reacts to this building pressure with increasing violence.The Cult of Rakdos already serves a megalomaniacal demon of chaos, so its members have no interest in seeing any other ambitious figure achieve supreme rulership over Ravnica. They fear that any other guild might gain enough power to overwhelm all the others and impose its own values on everyone. For this reason, they focus their efforts on subverting other guilds' schemes, by undermining popular and powerful leaders and interfering—often violently—with any effort to build a centralized concentration of authority.<br>The Azorius Senate currently stands as the greatest threat to the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;way of life. The cult targets Azorius senators and arresters for ridicule, harassment, and occasionally assassination. The Boros Legion's zealous pursuit of order and justice poses a similar threat. Although Boros's attention is focused on the Gruul at the moment,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;cultists are well aware that any sufficiently disruptive performance with a high enough body count could bring the wrath of the legion down on their heads. The overreaching of the Azorius and the self-righteous wrath of the Boros engender true fear in the anarchic&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;cultists, and the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;respond to fear with bloodshed.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/047-233.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Mathias Kollros" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/047-233.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/047-233.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Mathias Kollros<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,cult%20of%20rakdos" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,cult%20of%20rakdos" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/cult-of-rakdos.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Cult of Rakdos.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:06:54 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/046-246.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/046-246.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Orzhov Syndicate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/042-229.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Volkan Baga" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/042-229.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/042-229.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Volkan Baga“Representing the Orzhov was a tall, well-dressed noblewoman Jace didn't recognize. The identities of the Orzhov knights around her were concealed by full helmets; instead of faces they bore only the Orzhov's black sunburst symbol. Small, ugly, gray-skinned servant creatures attended to their black capes.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistWealth is power, and you absolutely&nbsp;can&nbsp;take it with you if you're an undying spirit living in decadent luxury on the ruling council of the Orzhov Syndicate. Built on the crushed dreams and broken bodies of citizens deeply indebted to the syndicate's banks and loan sharks, Orzhov's elaborate hierarchy of syndics, priests, and oligarchs exists for the single purpose of funneling wealth to the top. Beneath the twin facades of religious hierarchy and banking operation, Orzhov is an organized crime syndicate with its fingers in businesses across the city.The Orzhov's original function was both religious and financial, with the two functions closely related. As Ravnica's dominant church, the Orzhov continues to preach an oppressive message that equates sin with debt and promises forgiveness to those who make tithes and donations. As Ravnica's principal bank, it stores and secures the riches of the city, collecting interest at high rates to expand its own wealth. Its members truly believe that their work is necessary to the proper functioning of Ravnica. Although most other Ravnicans see the Orzhov for the corrupt organization it is, many people are still dazzled by the syndicate's promises of wealth, prestige, and longevity.The Ghost Council, also called the Obzedat, that leads the Orzhov founded the guild and signed the Guildpact, but it isn't clear which members of the original Obzedat might have faded from existence since then and which current members have joined since.The Orzhov are ruled by the iron-fisted Obzedat, a council consisting of the oldest and most powerful undead oligarchs. A vast hierarchy stretches out beneath them, so most of your interactions with the leadership of the guild are with people (or spirits) who occupy the rank just above yours. This hierarchy has corruption in it at every level, and at any time your superiors might be passing instructions down from on high or just using you to pursue their own agendas of greed and ambition.Orzhov churches and basilicas are scattered across the city, each one led by a ministrant with a staff of knights and syndics. These sites are centers of commerce clothed in the trappings of religion, where lowly borrowers come to seek atonement for their sins—atonement that is given in the form of debt and obligation.Orzhov attorneys and advokists maintain offices near New Prahv and other Azorius courts. Despite their proximity to law enforcement, these offices are centers of operation for Orzhov protection rackets and other criminal activities.The Orzhov Syndicate is dedicated to the quest for power. It sees the value in an organized, structured, law-abiding community, because it is adept at exploiting laws and structures for its own gain. It sees itself, in a perfect world, as the arbiter and enforcer of a social order that keeps everyone in their place and the Orzhov in the highest place.Increasing tensions in Ravnica have led to an atmosphere of instability, and to counter this, the Orzhov Syndicate promises the trappings of a stable, ordered life amid the chaos—for a price. The Orzhov believe that adherence to hierarchy is the key to success, and they find great comfort in the rigid structure of their guild.To boost their declining profits in a vacillating economy, the Orzhov have begun offering protection services, promising to shield their "customers" from both physical harm and fiscal disaster. These operations amount to racketeering, bringing with them the underlying threat that those who refuse to pay for protection become targets of the Orzhov's thugs and enforcers.<br>The Azorius are the greatest threat to Orzhov's operations. In times past, the Orzhov danced along the edges of the law and presented an appearance of legality, but the combination of an ever-expanding legal code and the guild's move into racketeering and other explicitly illegal activities has made it vulnerable to Azorius enforcement. So far, the Azorius have demonstrated more interest in cracking down on the chaotic activity of the Gruul and the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>, but Azorius arresters also routinely shut down Orzhov protection rackets and take enforcers into custody. To make matters worse, the Azorius Senate's increasing use of precognitive magic is proving difficult for the Orzhov to work around.So far, the syndicate's most effective tactic has been to increase the layers of separation between the day-to-day criminal operations of the guild and the leadership, ensuring that no matter how many street-level thugs and syndics are apprehended to fill the Azorius prisons, the guild's leadership remains intact. Contact between the oligarchs and lower-ranking members of the guild is increasingly rare in this situation, and even the pontiffs find it ever more difficult to arrange a hearing with their superiors.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,orzhov%20syndicate" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,orzhov%20syndicate" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/orzhov-syndicate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Orzhov Syndicate.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:04:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/042-229.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/042-229.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Izzet League]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/038-225.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Dmitry Burmak" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/038-225.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/038-225.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Dmitry Burmak“The Izzet mages weren't hard to find. After a couple of days of observation, Jace heard an explosion and saw a startled flight of birds from across the district. The plume of blue smoke was a telltale sign of one of the Izzet's pyrotechnic experiments. Jace tracked the source of the blast and spied two mages, a human and a goblin, outfitted with alchemical gadgetry and mizzium gauntlets. They emerged from a disused tunnel, leaving behind charred bricks and a haze of smoke, and their instruments crackled with energy. From what Jace had gathered, this was the Izzet style of research: keep adding energy until something blows up, then observe the results.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistThe Izzet are obsessive experimenters, combining a keen creative intellect with a short attention span. The original mandate of the Izzet guild was to provide solutions for public works projects (sewers, boilers, and roadways), but their increasingly far-fetched experiments satisfy only their insatiable curiosity. Sometimes their experiments yield useful technological advancements; other times they produce unintended mana geysers, spatial rifts, arcane portals, or huge explosions—all of which can be useful in their own way.The league's most grandiose experiments typically concern public works projects and elemental experimentation. These efforts use a methodology that relies on unexpected outcomes: all results are informative, even if they completely defy expectations. For example, an experiment that begins as the creation of a "hypermana focusing lens" might be renamed a "scram-range teleportal" once the researchers discover more properties of what they have fashioned. Then, after a few goblin volunteers vanish inside it, the apparatus gains the designation of "universal refuse disintegrator"—until the goblin volunteers are discovered alive, having been teleported far from the workshop. This sort of adjustment is par for the course in Izzet experiments; the "fiddle and find out" method is favored over any process of systematic scientific research.<br>The Izzet League is one of the few guilds whose founder, the dragon&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" target="_self">Niv-Mizzet</a>, remains its guildmaster, just as the guild continues to fulfill its original mission (even as its experiments go far beyond the guild's original mandate).<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" target="_self">Niv-Mizzet</a>, the original and current guildmaster of the Izzet League, is a fifteen-thousand-year-old, vain, temperamental, super-intelligent dragon. As he directs experiments throughout the guild, he values results over success, accepting and even anticipating that Izzet experiments will end in gloriously unpredictable ways. However, the dragon rarely concerns himself with the day-to-day running of the guild, preferring to craft long-range plans and let underlings implement the details.<br>Overseeing the daily operations of the guild is the purview of the Izmundi, a board of directors that assembles teams from among the rank and file of the Izzet League to carry out research according to&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" target="_self">Niv-Mizzet</a>'s directions. The Izmagnus is a smaller board with five to seven members (some members' identities remain secret) who serve as&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" target="_self">Niv-Mizzet</a>'s closest advisors.The Izzet League is organized into units designated as laboratories that specialize in certain fields of research. Though they all operate under the general guidance of the Izmundi, each laboratory is typically left alone to conduct its research. New fields of study emerge all the time, but the more established laboratories—each populated by hundreds of mages and their attendants—include the following:The&nbsp;Laboratory of Pyrology&nbsp;has a prominent facility in the guildhall, Nivix. Its emphasis is on heat, fire, and explosion.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Storms and Electricity&nbsp;focuses on controlling the weather as well as containing and conducting electrical energy. Its headquarters is in a spire atop Nivix, known as the Lightning Rod.Research into smelting and forging, most often using the magical metal known as mizzium, is conducted at the&nbsp;Laboratory of Metallurgy, which has a small outpost in the Tenth District's Smelting Quarter.The magical science of transmuting one substance to another is the study of the&nbsp;Laboratory of Alchemy.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Orientation, concerned with teleportation and spatial recombination, has multiple workshops that seem to appear and disappear at random.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Mimeography&nbsp;studies means of duplication.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Continuism&nbsp;emphasizes the study of temporal manipulation.Research into counter-magic and redirection takes place in the&nbsp;Laboratory of Arcane Geometry, which has a small presence in Prism University in the Tenth District.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Gravitational Inversion&nbsp;conducts research on means of flight and maintains a workshop near Augustin Station in the Tenth District.The&nbsp;Laboratory of Plasma-Dermatology&nbsp;places emphasis on the combining of opposing elements, with the purpose of creating creatures called weirds.Izzet laboratories function in a constant state of high energy that propels researchers from one experiment to the next. Some grand-scale experiments draw on the resources of an entire laboratory, while others are a lone visionary's labor of love.Izzet laboratories buzz with creative and often destructive energy, as countless researchers go about their business pushing the boundaries of knowledge. But the lure of discovery is anything but monolithic across the Izzet League.Humans, who make up the majority of the guild's mages, are fueled by limitless curiosity and sustained by their ability to approach any problem from a multitude of different angles.Goblins&nbsp;embody the Izzet's unrestrained enthusiasm for their endeavors. They epitomize the recklessness of Izzet mages, and some participate as subjects in hazardous experiments—even ones of their own devising. More often, they thrive in their role as attendants to researchers.Vedalken&nbsp;tend to be more focused, organized, and astute compared to their Izzet compatriots, and thus they often serve as leaders of projects in the guild's laboratories. Some vedalken are so obsessive about their work that they like to see to every detail themselves, rather than delegating any task to underlings or assistants. This attitude can irritate and alienate their guild mates—and put the vedalken in harm's way when an experiment goes awry.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/039-226.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Svetlin Velinov" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/039-226.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/039-226.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Svetlin VelinovThe Izzet League thirsts for knowledge, cherishes intellect, and speculates about the secrets of the multiverse. It brings to its scientific pursuits a flaming passion that turns its search for knowledge into an insatiable hunger, makes its cold intellect brilliantly fruitful, and widens its speculation into a search for connections between wildly disparate objects or concepts. It is manic in its expressions of creative energy, shifting from careful analysis to intuitive leap seemingly for no reason, always thinking outside the proverbial box. As the Izzet see it, unpredictable action, far from being antithetical to methodical research, has experimental value. In the words of one researcher, "The only action worth taking is one with an unknown outcome."<br>As Ravnica descends into increasing turmoil, the Izzet have further intensified their frenetic research, though now their efforts are mainly directed toward one outcome: the development of super-weapons. The suspicion that festers in the mind of the Izzet guildmaster, the ancient dragon&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#niv-mizzet_ggr" target="_self">Niv-Mizzet</a>, urges him to push his guild's research toward increasingly dangerous and volatile experimentation.For the rest of the guild members, the search for bigger and better weapons is mainly an opportunity to engage in all sorts of wild research while abandoning all outward pretense of safety or reason. Much of the guild's laboratory space has been converted into testing grounds that are capable of withstanding great discharges of magical energy.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,izzet%20league" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,izzet%20league" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/izzet-league.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Izzet League.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:02:03 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/038-225.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/038-225.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gruul Clans]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/034-221.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Kev Walker" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/034-221.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/034-221.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Kev Walker“Jace had never seen, or for that matter smelled, a Gruul war party at all. Their armor was made from animal hides and bones, and their weaponry was heavy pieces of scavenged city rubbish. Their skin was alive with tattoos, etched with a combination of magic, ink, and, Jace supposed, a considerable amount of pain. Each of them was a hulk of muscle, and Ruric Thar was the largest and mightiest of them all.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistThe Gruul Clans are a wild people in a civilized land, a loose affiliation of bands that squat on the fringes of Ravnican society. They shun the centers of civilization, which they see as a source of oppression and weakness, and instead haunt Ravnica's alleyways, abandoned zones, and ruins. They want to see the edifice of civilization torn down so the world can revert to the pure wilderness that thrived before the city grew to cover everything. Then the true order of nature can be restored—an unbridled and brutal state in which only the strong survive and the strongest rule.In a world covered with city streets and towering buildings, the Gruul are the most out of place, the most ill at ease, and the most eager to topple it all and start fresh. Constant ritualistic warfare reverberates among the clans, every skirmish reinforcing their doctrine of the survival of the fittest. They frequently send sorties into civilized areas to secure goods—and to wreak havoc.<br>The first leader of the Gruul was Cisarzim, a cyclops who was purportedly the ancestor of&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" target="_self">Borborygmos</a>, the current guildmaster. Cisarzim was called the Lord of Chaos, and his guild's original function as maintainers of Ravnica's natural places meant keeping his faction as remote as possible from the civilized parts of the world. The gradual expansion of the city, however, has driven the Gruul into smaller and smaller refuges.Gruul goblins live in colonies scattered at the edges of Gruul territory and civilized neighborhoods. They fight fiercely when threatened, punctuating their attacks with hisses and growls. When battle fury takes hold of a Gruul raiding group, it typically starts with the goblins, and after the battle, the surviving goblins are still frothing at the mouth and looking for someone to hit.<br>As a collection of disparate clans, the Gruul have no single leader and no headquarters. But the Gruul respect strength and are willing to follow a strong individual who points them in a direction they want to go anyway. For several decades, that position has been held by the mighty cyclops&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" target="_self">Borborygmos</a>, chief of the Burning Tree clan. His nihilistic anger inspires the rest of the Gruul, so when he calls on the other clans to join a raid, they usually agree. Even the fractious Gruul can see the benefit of banding together. The clans sometimes gather at Skarrg, a ruined palace in the rubblebelt adjoining the Tenth District. Here are descriptions of the clans:<br>Burning Tree Clan. The Burning Tree clan is the most fearsome of the Gruul Clans, as well as the largest and most diverse, with branches in several districts of Ravnica. The fear and awe inspired by&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#borborygmos_ggr" target="_self">Borborygmos</a>&nbsp;unifies its diverse membership. The Ravnican populace regards the symbol of the Burning Tree clan as the symbol for the entire Gruul guild.Ghor Clan. The Ghor clan is led by an ettin named Ruric Thar (or, perhaps more properly, Ruric and Thar, since the heads claim separate names). Of all the clans, the Ghor carry out the most frequent and savage assaults on Ravnica's citizenry. The clan is known for its audacity in forging encampments close to heavily populated districts.Scab Clan. Members of the Scab clan display scars and body modifications, which they view as expressions of the powerful rage they harbor within themselves. The clan has grown in influence by engulfing or destroying several smaller clans in recent years, but the leader of the Scabs, a corpulent giant known as Narbulg Nine Fingers, has not gone so far as to challenge the Burning Tree clan.<br>Slizt Clan. The Slizt clan is a clutch of sly, skittish warriors, consisting largely of reptilian humanoids called viashino (use the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#lizardfolk_mm" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#lizardfolk_mm" target="_self">lizardfolk</a>&nbsp;stat block in the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#mm" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#mm" target="_self">Monster Manual</a>&nbsp;to represent them), along with a few wily humans. This clan survives in the rubblebelts by taking up hiding places in high ground and ambushing its enemies with ranged attacks from above. Other Gruul regard the Slizt as skulkers and cowards, but nonetheless all are cautious when entering areas with elevated ruins. The home ground of the Slizt clan is the Husk, an area at the center of a vast rubblebelt featuring many large, ancient structures that have remained standing for generations.Gravel Hide Clan. The Gravel Hide clan believes that resilience is the truest measure of strength. Though a relatively new group, its members have already earned a reputation (almost certainly exaggerated) for shrugging off devastating attacks. The clan's leader, a hot-tempered goblin named Skorik Boulder Tooth, adorns himself with the shattered remnants of weapons that he has rent to bits with his own jaws.Zhur-Taa Clan. The Zhur-Taa clan advocates an extreme interpretation of the Old Ways. Central to this view is its belief in the imminent awakening of an ancient boar god—Ilharg, the Raze-Boar—who will lay waste to the overcivilized world. Led by a centaur druid called Nikya of the Old Ways, the Zhur-Taa pile up skulls as offerings to this god, and their druids perform guttural chants before and during battle that are said to be in the language of the old gods.Zhur-Taa druids are adept at summoning and training beasts as war-companions and mounts, and the clan's warriors wade into battle alongside giant boars, other beasts, and even wurms or hydras.Bolrac Clan. The most selective of all the Gruul Clans, the Bolrac clan denies membership to the smaller races. Its members are all enormous, lumbering brutes, primarily cyclopes, ogres, and giants. The clan's leadership changes frequently—sometimes daily, since battles for supremacy are as common as meals. The Bolrac clan specializes in bringing down massive structures using mauls and battering rams. The only thing the Bolrac love more than destroying something smaller than them is toppling, overrunning, and destroying something larger than them.Trogs. Some wandering hermits, known as trogs, find even the company of a clan to be too suffocating, so they spend their days alone in the wild places of Ravnica. These individuals are fierce, independent warriors who traverse the rubblebelts as apex predators. Trogs are notoriously short-tempered and impatient around others. Occasionally, they heed the call of the guildmaster to join in riots or festivals, but more often they conduct their own ceremonies and celebrations in private.So far as any philosophy can be said to underlie the Gruul way of life, it is about living in the now, with little concern for forethought, planning, or speculation. Impulse drives the actions of the Gruul Clans. They want to live their lives unimpeded, and they lash out when something tries to stand in their way. Emotion and impulsiveness drive them as they seek to do what they want, take what they want, and smash what they want.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,gruul%20clans" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,gruul%20clans" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/gruul-clans.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Gruul Clans.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 18:57:20 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/034-221.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/034-221.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[House Dimir]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/024-211.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Zezhou Chen" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/024-211.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/024-211.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Zezhou Chen“A vampire appeared out of the darkness, as quiet as a breeze. He was stripped to the waist despite the chill underground, and his eyes reflected light like a cat's. He floated effortlessly down from the upper reaches of the chamber, and alighted on the chamber floor near the two of them.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistHouse Dimir is Ravnica's dark secret: behind a facade of respectable messengers and reporters lurks an association of spies and assassins whose existence is barely suspected by the populace at large. Secrecy is both House Dimir's best weapon and its best defense, and much of the guild's work is hidden even from other members. Dimir agents leave no trace of their covert activities, warping the memories of witnesses to their crimes and even wiping their own minds to remove any evidence of their completed assignments.The first guildmaster of House Dimir was a vampire named Szadek, whose organization agreed to serve as Ravnica's couriers, information brokers, and librarians. But Szadek also used his guild's expertise at gathering information to build a vast spy network, and before long, the secret operations of the guild vastly outweighed its overt ones. Eventually the guild disappeared into the shadows, and most Ravnicans came to doubt its existence. An immortal entity, Szadek ruled the guild for ten thousand years until he was arrested and killed in the turmoil of the Decamillennial Celebration.<br>House Dimir has a clandestine aspect hidden from all but its most important members. The guildmaster,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#lazav_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#lazav_ggr" target="_self">Lazav</a>, and his direct contacts guide and manipulate the covert operations of the guild. Members of House Dimir ultimately receive their orders from this source without having any idea of who issued the order or why. Messages to agents are funneled through thought strands (see "Spell:&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/spells.html#encode%20thoughts_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/spells.html#encode%20thoughts_ggr" target="_self">Encode Thoughts</a>" later in this section) and telepathic couriers.By design, you don't have much interaction with other members of your guild. You might never meet your primary guild contact face to face, instead receiving assignments and sending reports by way of secret message drops and codes.House Dimir is all about secrets and misinformation, even where its own members are concerned. Any given Dimir agent knows of no more than a handful of alleyway contacts and dossier drop spots. One agent knows another only by a code name, or receives communications only at a particular meeting spot at a specific place and time. Every self-proclaimed expert with an opinion on the matter has a theory about the guild's intentions, and all those guesses about Dimir's motivations and pursuits contradict each other, frustrating any attempt to get to the truth of things. The public face of Dimir remains inscrutable, which some interpret as the best evidence that the guild's true plans mean something dire for the Ravnican populace.To House Dimir, knowledge is power. The guild hungers to learn everything it doesn't already know, especially the weaknesses of its adversaries, and to exploit those weaknesses for its own gain. Conversely, the house holds its own secrets tightly, because it doesn't want its enemies to turn the tables. The Dimir lurk in the shadows, methodically gathering the knowledge they need to remake Ravnica to their advantage.House Dimir's progress toward its goals depends on a web woven from meticulously gathered intelligence. Unpredictable behavior by other guilds can destabilize that web. When the Boros take sudden, forceful action inspired by an unexpected burst of zeal, the Dimir can be caught off guard. The Selesnya behave predictably on the whole, but the members of the conclave are so numerous that it can be hard for the Dimir to keep track of their activities. Of all the other guilds, the Izzet and the Gruul concern the Dimir the most; their erratic methods of decision-making, combined with their unflinching approach to danger, can quickly undermine any Dimir strategy designed to contain them.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,house%20dimir" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,house%20dimir" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/house-dimir.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/House Dimir.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 18:42:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/024-211.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/024-211.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Boros Legion]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/019-206.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Aaron Miller" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/019-206.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/019-206.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Aaron Miller“A brown-bearded, broad-chested man clad in massive-shouldered plate armor led a battalion of soldiers, the symbol of the Boros Legion emblazoned on white cloth draped over their armor. Their soldiers were a variety of races, including humans, a minotaur with a permanent scowl on her face, an impatient-looking goblin, and even some kind of humanoid fire elemental, whose Boros armor floated in protective positions over its animate flame.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistClad in shining armor and fueled by righteous zeal, the soldiers of the Boros Legion take up steel against the corruption and lawlessness that gnaw at the soul of Ravnica. Combining the force of law with the military strength to back it up, the Boros work to forge Ravnica into a just society, a safe and healthy community for all. From garrisons throughout the sprawling city, disciplined, stalwart soldiers are dispatched to stand firm against Gruul raids, Dimir infiltration, Golgari corruption, and the subtle influence of more nefarious foes.<br>The archangel Razia was the original guildmaster of the Boros Legion, which was established to serve as Ravnica's standing army. Razia served as its guildmaster for almost ten thousand years. Legend says that all the other angels of Ravnica were created in the image of this semidivine figure, and her death was devastating to the guild.&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#aurelia_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#aurelia_ggr" target="_self">Aurelia</a>, the current angelic guildmaster, is the third to hold that title.Minotaurs have a reputation for being both fierce warriors and clever strategists. Thick of muscle, stout of heart, and possessing a burning love of justice and the battlefield, they have become the steel spine of the Boros Legion. Generations of minotaurs of the Ordruun family line have served with honor and distinction, claiming more than fifteen generals to their lineage.<br>Angels occupy the highest tier of the Boros hierarchy, from the guildmaster&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#aurelia_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#aurelia_ggr" target="_self">Aurelia</a>&nbsp;down to the hosts of holy warriors and advisors in leadership roles. Their opinions and advice are deeply respected in the guild, though the angels aren't above engaging in the machinations of mortal politics. The angels include the wise, strategic warleaders; the holy champions and paragons of war known as firemanes; and battleforce angels, who form the bulk of the legion's angelic warriors.From the perspective of the average Boros soldier, the angels embody the ideals the Boros hold dear. Few mortal soldiers gain admission into the presence of the warleaders and other powerful angels, but battleforce angels fight at the forefront of the legion's ranks, and they form strong friendships with mortals under such life-and-death circumstances. Boros paladins are the members most likely to converse with the angels and be charged with implementing their plans.The garrison commanders who convey the angels' commands are accessible to the ordinary soldier. In addition to Sunhome, the Boros maintain smaller garrisons throughout the Tenth District, at least one in each of the six precincts.Wherever criminals exploit others, petty tyrants make grabs for power, or violence erupts and leaves devastation in its wake, Boros soldiers are there fighting to make things right.The Boros Legion is defined by the tension between its goal of establishing order and harmony and the fiery zeal that drives many of its members. The guild stands for peace and justice, which can be established only through the rule of law. Its moral stance is fundamentally good, as it strives to protect the innocent and powerless from oppression and exploitation. At the same time, members of the legion are passionate about their pursuit of justice, spurred by their righteous wrath into action against evil and injustice. Ironically, this means that individual members sometimes break the rules they are charged with enforcing, cleaving to the spirit of the law when the letter no longer serves justice.Because the Guildpact—the one force on Ravnica that can keep the guilds from destroying each other—is now embodied in a single, unreliable person who vanishes for weeks or months at a time, the legion is in a heightened state of vigilance. In this time of uncertainty, the Boros are on constant alert for military threats. They work to maintain their fortifications to ensure that they aren't overrun by Gruul marauders. Construction proceeds on new strongholds near Gruul territories, but in general the Boros prepare for a military threat the same way they always have—by fielding the stronger army.The angels are also bracing for a subtler threat: the danger of infiltration by House Dimir. The Boros are becoming increasingly aware of the possibility that their guild could be undermined from within. Security at garrison buildings is vigilant, with angels watching the entrances at all times for spies.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,boros%20legion" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,boros%20legion" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/boros-legion.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Boros Legion.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 18:01:37 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/019-206.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/019-206.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Azorius Senate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/015-202.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Craig J Spearing" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/015-202.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/015-202.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Craig J Spearing“Officer Lavinia stood before the enormous double doors that led into the highest spire of New Prahv, the lair of the guildmaster. To look at her, nothing would seem out of place: her cape spilled elegantly from her officer's armor, her sword shone like a decorative piece one would hang above a mantel, and her three-sided medals displayed her district-spanning rank.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The Secretist<br>Bringing order from chaos—that is the mission of the Azorius Senate. Without the extensive legal code crafted and enforced by the Azorius, society would crumble, transforming Ravnica into a field of rubble where the Gruul and the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;do whatever they please. The Azorius carry this weighty responsibility with stoic pride, and they perform their work of legislation, investigation, and enforcement with steely determination.The first guildmaster of the Azorius Senate was a sphinx named Azor. He was the author of the original Guildpact, as well as the creator of the elaborate contingency plan that resulted in the creation of the Living Guildpact. The Azorius Senate was meant to carry on his legacy by serving as the legislative body of Ravnica.<br>The Azorius Senate is supported by three branches, called columns, each led by an arbiter (also called a capital). The capitals of the three columns form the Triumvirate, which advises the guildmaster, Supreme Judge&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#isperia_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#isperia_ggr" target="_self">Isperia</a>, an ancient and wise sphinx.The&nbsp;Sova Column&nbsp;consists of judges and the extensive legal apparatus surrounding them. It is tasked with adjudicating and arbitrating the effects of the law. The column employs legal aides, pages, librarians, experts on precedent, advocates for the accused, public prosecutors, and judges.The&nbsp;Jelenn Column&nbsp;writes and enacts the laws of Ravnica, involving the efforts not just of the designated legislators but also a network of bureaucrats: aides, writers, researchers, lobbyists, clerks, and so on.The&nbsp;Lyev Column&nbsp;enforces the law as Ravnica's police force. The many-leveled hierarchy of the Lyev Column includes arresters, investigators, officers, and lawmages. The Lyev Column is also venturing into the work of managing surveillance and precognition. Most adventuring characters, by their nature and because of their capabilities, are associated with the active work of the Lyev Column rather than the behind-the-scenes activity of the other columns.The Azorius Senate's ultimate goal is the perfection of society. They want to protect the people of Ravnica and foster a community of peace and harmony. A society's values, they contend, are reflected in the laws it creates. Something is good if it is lawful. To the Azorius, the highest virtue is a society built on stability and order, and the guild's elaborate system of laws is structured to prevent wrongdoing first and foremost, even at the expense of certain liberties. The Azorius can act as a benevolent proactive force that keeps evildoers in check, but it can also act as an oppressive bureaucratic force that stifles freedom and expression.In the absence of the Living Guildpact, the Azorius are uncertain who is supposed to maintain balance among the guilds. As a group, they are convinced that the system can't be disrupted, but they are challenged by the reality that the one person who is meant to hold their world together never seems to be around. The Azorius Senate is invoking emergency powers with increasing frequency, and the Lyev Column's enforcers are wielding an ever-growing amount of influence.The Azorius guild embraces the belief that Ravnican society has come too far to succumb to chaos. Civilization can be saved only through the guidance of a strong, safety-focused government. In the mind of the Azorius, the threat of chaos is imminent. They believe it is time to face facts and do whatever is necessary to protect the people and preserve the force of law.<br>The Azorius, as always, see agents of disorder as their greatest enemies. They have cracked down on the Gruul Clans and imposed a variety of creatively written laws outlawing that guild's presence in as many public places as possible. The Azorius also abhor the satirical shows of the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;(in part because the Azorius are frequently ridiculed by&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#rakdos_ggr" target="_self">Rakdos</a>&nbsp;performers) and attempt to curb them with new decrees about public performances. In response to attempts by other guilds to edge their way around the system, the Azorius routinely create new laws to support or countermand old ones.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,azorius%20senate" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,azorius%20senate" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/azorius-senate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Azorius Senate.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 17:44:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/015-202.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/015-202.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Simic Combine]]></title><description><![CDATA[“The Simic representative was a stern-looking mage whose parentage appeared to be partly human and partly aquatic, possibly merfolk; he rode astride a creature that seemed the offspring of a giant, blue-carapaced crab and an irate squid. The Simic squad was rounded out by a host of mages clad in scale armor, and improbable hybrid fusions of scaled, finned, and shelled creatures.”— Doug Beyer,&nbsp;Return to Ravnica: The SecretistThe secrets of life are revealed in the laboratories of the Simic, and their research notes plumb and catalog nature's wonders. Their original mission was to oversee issues of public health, but the Simic came to believe that complete health—of individuals and of society as a whole—depends on the mutual adaptation of nature and civilization to one another. Thus, biological experimentation has always been among its primary concerns.Historically, the guild's approach to its mission has been one of incremental progress toward a utopian ideal of thriving biology, and it remains more aloof from politics than other guilds. Its fundamental mission remains unchanged by the current political instability, and the isolation of its laboratories protects most Simic guild members from immediate harm.Little is known about the combine's founder, except that this individual's first or family name was Simic.Vast sinkholes called zonots are the primary geographic divisions among the Simic. Each zonot pierces layer upon layer of crumbled city as it descends deep below the surface and connects to ancient, long-forgotten ocean waters. A zonot is a distinct Simic habitat with its own culture and ecosystem, as well as a leader called a Speaker. The Speakers of all nine zonots form the Speakers' Chamber, and they elect a Prime Speaker from among them to serve as the Simic guildmaster.&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#zegana_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#zegana_ggr" target="_self">Zegana</a>, the current Prime Speaker, is the Speaker of Zonot One, which is located in a remote, sparsely inhabited part of Ravnica far from the political activity of the Tenth District.The Simic guildhall, Zameck, is located in Zonot Seven within Precinct Five of Ravnica's Tenth District. A huge chamber just below the street serves as the gathering place for all the Speakers, as well as a location where non-Simic visitors can meet with the Prime Speaker or other combine emissaries.Two philosophical principles, in tension with each other, combine to give the Simic Combine its unique approach to science and nature. In traditional Simic thought, these principles are called the Holdfast and the Upwelling.The Holdfast principle, named for the biological mechanism that keeps kelp and sponges anchored to the sea floor, advises members of the Simic Combine never to stray so far from nature that they become "adrift." It espouses the idea that nature left undisturbed will evolve toward adaptive traits and increased strength. Nature will flourish and grow, and every creature will find its proper niche in the ecosystem where it can thrive.The Upwelling principle, named for the phenomenon of nutrient-rich water rising to the ocean surface, advocates that the new and enlivened should replace the old and depleted in an unending cycle, bringing constant refreshment and renewal. This principle accounts for the combine's analytical bent and its emphasis on knowledge as a means of transformation. Learning the secrets of the universe lets you shape the world as you desire. The Upwelling encourages every creature to discover its full potential.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/058-243.webp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" title="Art credit: Willian Murai" href="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/058-243.webp" target="_self"></a><img src="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/058-243.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">&nbsp;Willian MuraiThe Holdfast encourages the Simic to promote nature; the Upwelling urges them to perfect nature. The end result is the same: a hastened system of evolution that brings out the best in every creature's nature. But different factions within the Simic Combine interpret these principles in their own ways.<br>The leadership of the Simic Combine represents the traditional philosophy of the Utopians. Their vision is of an ideal world in which nature and civilization exist in balance, in which natural life adapts to life in the midst of modern civilization and the civilized world adapts to accommodate these creatures. Utopians generally interpret the Holdfast principle as being about staying rooted in nature, and the Upwelling as concerned with slow, predictable, cyclical improvement. So they remain hidden in their subaquatic laboratories, pursuing their research while isolated from the volatile interrelationships among the other guilds. Prime Speaker&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#zegana_ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/bestiary.html#zegana_ggr" target="_self">Zegana</a>&nbsp;encourages that isolationist attitude.At the same time, a growing faction within the Simic believes that an all-out war among the guilds is inevitable, given the growing unrest in the city. These members, the Adaptationists, believe that the guilds exist in a fragile ecosystem in which the slightest imbalance can have cascading effects. With an absent Living Guildpact failing to maintain the balance, only catastrophe can result. The Simic must change in order to survive, and slow, small steps in pursuit of an ideal vision aren't enough. The future of the guild is in imminent danger, and the Simic need to focus on survival. Adaptationists tend to interpret the Holdfast as being about defense and security, and the Upwelling as a call for sudden, disruptive growth.As befits members of a guild of scientists, the Adaptationists' preparations for war include the creation of soldiers that are magically and biologically adapted. The Guardian Project has yielded hybrids that combine human, elf, or vedalken stock with the characteristics of crabs, fish, jellyfish, and a variety of other creatures to give them natural armor and weapons, gills, venomous stings, and other combat-focused adaptations.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,simic%20combine" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2,simic%20combine" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/simic-combine.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Simic Combine.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 17:36:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/058-243.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://5e.tools/img/book/GGR/058-243.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Guild Primer]]></title><description><![CDATA[The ten guilds are the lifeblood of <a data-href="Ravnica" href="setting/ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>, making up the foundation of its society. They are voluntary associations led by guild masters, but that's the extent of their resemblance to the craft and merchant guilds found on most Dungeons &amp; Dragons worlds. They include many different kinds of organizations:
<br>A government body, the <a data-href="Azorius Senate" href="guilds/azorius-senate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Azorius Senate</a>
<br>A military force, the <a data-href="Boros Legion" href="guilds/boros-legion.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Boros Legion</a>
<br>An espionage network, <a data-href="House Dimir" href="guilds/house-dimir.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">House Dimir</a>
<br>An association of raiders, the <a data-href="Gruul Clans" href="guilds/gruul-clans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gruul Clans</a>
<br>Two scientific research institutions, the <a data-href="Izzet League" href="guilds/izzet-league.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Izzet League</a> and the <a data-href="Simic Combine" href="guilds/simic-combine.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Simic Combine</a>
<br>An organized crime family, the <a data-href="Orzhov Syndicate" href="guilds/orzhov-syndicate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Orzhov Syndicate</a>
<br>Raucous performance troupes collectively known as the <a data-href="Cult of Rakdos" href="guilds/cult-of-rakdos.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cult of Rakdos</a>, which bends to the whims of a powerful demon
<br>Two widely divergent groups devoted to nature, the <a data-href="Golgari Swarm" href="guilds/golgari-swarm.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Golgari Swarm</a> and the <a data-href="Selesnya Conclave" href="guilds/selesnya-conclave.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Selesnya Conclave</a>
Citizens of Ravnica aren't born into guilds. An individual can choose to belong to any guild—or no guild. Some guilds, such as Selesnya and Boros, actively recruit new members, while others simply accept those who seek membership. People within a family might join different guilds, which can lead to strong connections between the guilds in question or to painful animosity in families whose members follow different paths.Even though citizens can choose their guild associations, long-standing traditions steer certain individuals toward a particular guild. For example, it would be highly unusual for a Devkarin elf (a dark elf) to join any guild other than the Golgari, and the Ordruun line of minotaurs has provided the Boros armies with generations of offspring. Members of certain races are also drawn to specific guilds, as noted in the description of each of guild.You establish your character's membership in a guild by choosing that guild's background from among those detailed in this chapter. This book assumes that you have chosen a guild and that you maintain your association with it throughout your life. As a result, your choice of guild can play a more significant role than most backgrounds do in shaping what your character does now, not just what you accomplished in the past.<br>The backgrounds associated with guilds in this chapter work like those in the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#phb" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#phb" target="_self">Player's Handbook</a>, giving you proficiencies, languages, equipment, and suggested characteristics (personality traits, ideals, bonds, and flaws). Each guild entry also provides personal contacts; suggestions for your alignment, race, and class; and a list of spells that you can add to your spell list if you're a member of a spell casting class.The spellcasters of Ravnica's guilds have a style of magic specific to their guild. A guild's description includes a list of guild spells that epitomize the type of magic the guild favors. The Boros Legion, for example, tends to prefer using spells of fire magic and holy light, and its guild spell list reflects that emphasis.If you play a character who has the Spell casting or the Pact Magic class feature, your guild spells are added to the spell list for your class, thereby expanding the spell options available to you.As a benefit of your guild membership, you have contacts both inside and outside the guild. Contacts are useful resources in the urban environment of Ravnica, where a friendly face can be more valuable than gold.<br>As stated in the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#phb" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#phb" target="_self">Player's Handbook</a>, bonds represent your connections to people, places, and events in the world. Contacts are people you have a connection to, but they're not necessarily bonds. People can be bonds if they inspire you, motivate you, or make you act against your best interests. (They can represent flaws if their existence amounts to a weakness for you.) Contacts, in comparison, are simply people you know. They might be friends, rivals, or even family members, but their relationship with you is rarely as strong as with a bond.Although the tables of contacts in this chapter describe non player characters who are members of guilds (your own and others), you are likely to acquire guild-less contacts as well. NPCs such as goblin gang leaders, minotaur bartenders, and vedalken tailors all go about their lives in the shadow of the guilds but divorced from those groups' intrigue and politics.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr,2" target="_self">Source</a>]]></description><link>guilds/guild-primer.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Guilds/Guild Primer.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 17:25:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Index]]></title><description><![CDATA[Welcome to the lore for Fey of Ravnica!Here is a set of quick links for you to peruse.<a data-href="Character Creation" href="mechanics/character-creation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Character Creation</a><br>
<a data-href="Setting details" href="setting/setting-details.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Setting details</a><br>
<a data-href="Ravnica" href="setting/ravnica.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ravnica</a>]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Index.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 16:55:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ravnica]]></title><description><![CDATA[If you want to know way more about Ravnica than you need to read <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://5e.tools/book.html#ggr" target="_self">this.</a> If you keep reading that whole book you'll know more than the DM does.]]></description><link>setting/ravnica.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Setting/Ravnica.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:26:34 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>